

305 N. University St., Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN 47907

□ (+1) 765-409-0693 | 🗷 xinruw@purdue.edu | 🏕 https://xinruw.github.io/ | 🛅 Xinru Wang | 🎓 Xinru Wang

# Research Interest

My research lies at the intersection of human-computer interaction (HCI) and explainable AI (XAI). I utilize both experimental and computational approaches to explore Al-assisted human decision making, and finally seek to enhance Al systems for effective human interaction.

## **Education**

**Purdue University** West Lafayette, IN, US

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE, GPA: 3.93/4.00

Aug. 2019 - Present

Beijing, China

Advisor: Ming Yin

**Peking University** Beijing, China

B.S. IN PSYCHOLOGY (DUAL DEGREE), GPA: 3.51/4.00 Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2019

**Peking University** 

B.S. IN INTELLIGENCE SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, GPA: 3.65/4.00 Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019

• Thesis: "Analysis of MOOC Forum Data towards AI Support"

# **Professional Experience**

**Megagon Labs** Mountain View, CA, US

RESEARCH INTERN

May. 2023 - Aug. 2023

• Mentor: Hannah Kim, Zhengjie Miao

**Purdue University** West Lafayette, IN, US

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2019 - Present

- · Advisor: Ming Yin, Assistant Professor
- · Conducted large-scale online human-subject experiments to evaluate how different AI explanation dynamics impact human decision-making
- · Proposed a space of three-component (i.e. inference + utility + selection) human behavior models in Al-assisted decision making.

**University of Michigan** Ann Arbor, MI, US

SUMMER RESEARCH INTERN

Jul. 2018 - Sep. 2018

- · Advisor: Lionel Robert, Professor
- · Investigated bi-directional trust in semi-autonomous vehicles through user testing, data extraction, and trust modeling.

**Kendall Square Capital** Beijing, China

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN Jan. 2019 - Apr. 2019

• Extracted time-series features from the limit order book data for prediction of mid-price movement in high frequency trading.

DiDi Beijing, China

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN Sep. 2018 - Jan. 2019

· Implemented machine learning models to predict drivers' order-taken behavior and waiting-time on a million-scale database.

#### **Publications**

# The Effects of AI Biases and Explanations on Human Decision Fairness: A Case Study of Bidding in Rental Housing

Xinru Wang, Chen Liang, Ming Yin. IJCAI 2023

Who Should I Trust: AI or Myself? Leveraging Human and AI Correctness Likelihood to Promote Appropriate Trust in AI-Assisted Decision-Making

Shuai Ma, Ying Lei, Xinru Wang, Chengbo Zheng, Chuhan Shi, Ming Yin, Xiaojuan Ma. CHI 2023

Watch Out For Updates: Understanding the Effects of Model Explanation Updates in AI-Assisted Decision Making Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. CHI 2023

Will You Accept the AI Recommendation? Predicting Human Behavior in AI-Assisted Decision Making

Xinru Wang, Zhuoran Lu, Ming Yin. WWW 2022

#### Effects of Explanations in AI-Assisted Decision Making: Principles and Comparisons

Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. ACM Transactions on Interactive Intelligent Systems (TiiS), 2022

## Are Explanations Helpful? A Comparative Study of the Effects of Explanations in Al-Assisted Decision-Making

Xinru Wang, Ming Yin. IUI 2021

# Patent\_

#### **Recommendation Method for Recipes Based on Deep Learning**

Xinru Wang, Yichun Wang, Zhilou Yu. CN107665254A, Patent filed in Feb. 2018 (In Chinese)

# **Teaching**

#### CS471 Introduction to Artificial Intelligence, Purdue University

Head Teaching Assistant

Fall 2022, Spring 2023

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2019

CS242 Introduction to Data Science, Purdue University

Teaching Assistant Spring 2020

CS38001 Python Programming, Purdue University

Teaching Assistant Fall 2019, Spring 2020

# Talk

#### Understanding Human Behavior in Al-Assisted Decision Making: Experiments and Models

Apr. 2022

MIDAS Future Leaders Summit 2022, University of Michigan

# **Professional Service**

#### **Program Committee**

• CHI HCXAI workshop 2022 & 2023, FAccT 2023

#### Reviewer

• TiiS, CHI 2023, CHI 2023 Late-Breaking Work

#### **Student Volunteer**

• SIGIR 2018

# Honors & Awards

2023	<b>Graduate Teaching Award</b> , Purdue University Department of Computer Science	West Lafayette, IN, US
2018	Academic Excellence Award, Peking University (top 10%)	Beijing, China
2018	Fei-Xun Scholarship, Peking University	Beijing, China
2016	Academic Excellence Award, Peking University (top 15%)	Beijing, China
2016	May 4th Scholarship, Peking University	Beijing, China

### Skills

**Programming** Python, R, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, SQL, MATLAB, C/C++, Java

**Frameworks** Pandas, Numpy, sklearn, Meteor

**Languages** Chinese, English (GRE 162+170+3.5, TOEFL 111)

August 29, 2023 Xinru Wang · Résumé 2